I'd like to show you a video of some of the models
أود أن اريكم فيديو لبعض العينات
I work with.
التي اعمل معها
They're all the perfect size, and they don't have an ounce of fat.
جميعهم مثاليي البنية، ولا يحملون اية دهون
Did I mention they're gorgeous?
ألم أقل لكم انهن فائقات الجمال؟
And they're scientific models? (Laughs)
و أنها نماذج علمية؟ (ضحك)
As you might have guessed, I'm a tissue engineer,
كما قد تكونوا توقعتم، أنا مهندسة أنسجة حيوية
and this is a video of some of the beating heart
وهذا شريط فيديو لبعض من القلب النابض
that I've engineered in the lab.
التي بنيتها في المختبر.
And one day we hope that these tissues
ويوم ما.. نأمل بان تكون هذه الأنسجة
can serve as replacement parts for the human body.
بمثابة اعضاء بديلة لجسم الإنسان.
But what I'm going to tell you about today
ولكن ما سوف اخبركم به اليوم
is how these tissues make awesome models.
هو كيف ستكون هذه الأنسجة نماذج رائعة.
Well, let's think about the drug screening process for a moment.
حسنا، دعونا للحظة نفكر بعملية اختبار الادوية
You go from drug formulation, lab testing, animal testing,
ننتقل من صياغة الادوية، لاختبارات المعامل، للاختبارات الحيوانية
and then clinical trials, which you might call human testing,
ومن ثم للاختبارات الصيدلية، او ما نسميها الاختبارات البشرية،
before the drugs get to market.
قبل وصول الأدوية إلى السوق
It costs a lot of money, a lot of time,
تكلف العملية الكثير من المال، والكثير من الوقت،
and sometimes, even when a drug hits the market,
وفي بعض الأحيان، حتى عندما تنزل الأدوية إلى السوق،
it acts in an unpredictable way and actually hurts people.
فإنه لايمكن التنبئ بنتائجها وقد تضر الناس
And the later it fails, the worse the consequences.
وكل ما تأخرت هذه النتائج، كلما زادت المساوئ.
It all boils down to two issues. One, humans are not rats,
وكل شيء ينحدر لسببين. الأول، الناس ليسوا فئراناً،
and two, despite our incredible similarities to one another,
والثاني، رغم التشابه الكبير بين بعضنا البعض،
actually those tiny differences between you and I
فان تلك الاختلافات الصغيرة بيني أنا وأنت
have huge impacts with how we metabolize drugs
لها آثار ضخمة على كيفية أستجابتنا للأدوية
and how those drugs affect us.
وكيفية تأثيرها علينا.
So what if we had better models in the lab
إذا ماذا لو كان عندنا نماذج أفضل في المختبر
that could not only mimic us better than rats
و بإمكانها محاكاتنا ليس فقط أفضل من الفئران
but also reflect our diversity?
ولكن يمكنها ان تعكس تنوعنا ايضاً؟
Let's see how we can do it with tissue engineering.
دعونا نرى كيف يمكننا أن نقوم بذلك من خلال هندسة الأنسجة.
One of the key technologies that's really important
واحدة من التقنيات الرئيسية والمهة حقاً
is what's called induced pluripotent stem cells.
هو ما يسمى بالخلايا الجذعية المستحثة المحفزة: "induced pluripotent stem cells"
They were developed in Japan pretty recently.
طورت هذه الخلايا في اليابان مؤخرا
Okay, induced pluripotent stem cells.
حسنا، الخلايا الجذعية المستحثة المحفزة.
They're a lot like embryonic stem cells
أنها شبيهة جداً للخلايا الجذعية الجنينية "embryonic stem cells"
except without the controversy.
باستثناء غياب الجدل حولها.
We induce cells, okay, say, skin cells,
نحن نحفز الخلايا، حسنا، لنقل، خلايا الجلد،
by adding a few genes to them, culturing them,
بإضافة بعض الجينات إليها، إنباتها،
and then harvesting them.
ومن ثم حصدها.
So they're skin cells that can be tricked,
لذا فانها خلايا جلدية يمكن اللعب بها،
kind of like cellular amnesia, into an embryonic state.
بتحويلها من حالة فقدان الذاكرة الخلوية، الى حالة جنينية.
So without the controversy, that's cool thing number one.
وبدون الوقوع بالجدل، فهذا الشيء الرائع الآول.
Cool thing number two, you can grow any type of tissue
الشيء الرائع الثاني، هو انه يمكنك زراعة أي نوع من الأنسجة منها
out of them: brain, heart, liver, you get the picture,
كالدماغ، القلب، الكبد.. الصورة واضحة،
but out of your cells.
ولكن من خلاياك!
So we can make a model of your heart, your brain
فيمكننا أن نخلق نموذجا من قلبك، او عقلك
on a chip.
على شريحة.
Generating tissues of predictable density and behavior
استحداث أنسجة ذات كثافة وسلوك متوقع
is the second piece, and will be really key towards
هي الخطوة الثانية، وسوف تكون حقاً المفتاح نحو
getting these models to be adopted for drug discovery.
الحصول على هذه النماذج لاستعمالها في اكتشاف العلاج.
And this is a schematic of a bioreactor we're developing in our lab
وهذا هو الرسم التخطيطي لمفاعل حيوي قيد التطوير في مختبرنا
to help engineer tissues in a more modular, scalable way.
للمساعدة في هندسة الأنسجة بطريقة أكثر مرونة، وقابلة للتطوير.
Going forward, imagine a massively parallel version of this
لنمضي قدماً، تخيل نسخة موازية على نطاق واسع لهذا
with thousands of pieces of human tissue.
مع الآلاف من قطع الأنسجة البشرية.
It would be like having a clinical trial on a chip.
ستكون بمثابة القيام بتجارب بشرية على شريحة.
But another thing about these induced pluripotent stem cells
ولكن شيء آخر حول هذه الخلايا الجذعية المستحثة المحفزة
is that if we take some skin cells, let's say,
هو أنه إذا ما أخذنا بعض خلايا الجلد، دعنا نقول،
from people with a genetic disease
من المصابين بمرض وراثي
and we engineer tissues out of them,
ونقوم بهندسة أنسجة منهم،
we can actually use tissue-engineering techniques
فيمكننا في الواقع استخدام تقنيات هندسة الأنسجة
to generate models of those diseases in the lab.
لتوليد نماذج من تلك الأمراض في المختبر.
Here's an example from Kevin Eggan's lab at Harvard.
هنا مثال من مختبر كيفن إيجان في جامعة هارفارد.
He generated neurons
لقد استحدث خلايا عصبية
from these induced pluripotent stem cells
من تلك الخلايا الجذعية المستحثة المحفزة
from patients who have Lou Gehrig's Disease,
من المرضى الذين يعانون من مرض لو جيهريج "Lou Gehrig"
and he differentiated them into neurons, and what's amazing
وقد طورهم الى خلايا عصبية، والمذهل
is that these neurons also show symptoms of the disease.
هو أن هذه الخلايا العصبية تظهر ايضاً أعراض المرض.
So with disease models like these, we can fight back
لذا فانه مع نماذج للمرض مثل هذه، فانه بامكاننا التصدي للأمراض
faster than ever before and understand the disease better
أسرع من أي وقت مضى، وبامكاننا فهم المرض أفضل
than ever before, and maybe discover drugs even faster.
من أي وقت مضى، وربما يمكننا ايضاً من اكتشاف العلاج أسرع.
This is another example of patient-specific stem cells
وهذا مثال آخر للخلايا الجذعية الخاصة بالمريض
that were engineered from someone with retinitis pigmentosa.
والتي تمت هندستها من شخص معه التهاب الشبكية الصباغي"retinitis pigmentosa"
This is a degeneration of the retina.
وهذا تنكس شبكية العين"degeneration of the retina"
It's a disease that runs in my family, and we really hope
وهو مرض في عائلتي، ونحن نأمل حقاً
that cells like these will help us find a cure.
أن الخلايا مثل هذه ستساعدنا على إيجاد علاج.
So some people think that these models sound well and good,
إذاً فالبعض يعتقدون أن هذه النماذج تبدو سليمة وجيدة،
but ask, "Well, are these really as good as the rat?"
ولكن، أهذه حقاً "فعالة أكثر من الفئران"؟
The rat is an entire organism, after all,
لان الفأر كائن حي كامل،
with interacting networks of organs.
يحوي شبكات مرتبطة من الأجهزة المتفاعلة.
A drug for the heart can get metabolized in the liver,
فالدواء الذي للقلب يمتص ايضاً في الكبد،
and some of the byproducts may be stored in the fat.
وبعض المنتجات الثانوية قد تخزن في الدهون.
Don't you miss all that with these tissue-engineered models?
الا يغيب كل ذلك عن هذه النماذج النسيجية المهندسة؟
Well, this is another trend in the field.
حسنا، هذا اتجاه آخر في هذا المجال.
By combining tissue engineering techniques with microfluidics,
من خلال الجمع بين تقنيات الأنسجة الهندسة مع الموائع الدقيقة
the field is actually evolving towards just that,
المجال حالياً يتطور نحو هذا الإتجاه تماما،
a model of the entire ecosystem of the body,
نموذج لكامل النظام الإيكولوجي للجسم،
complete with multiple organ systems to be able to test
متكامل مع العديد من أنظمة الجسم لتكون قادرة على اختبار
how a drug you might take for your blood pressure
كيف يمكن لدواء تأخده من أجل ضغط الدم
might affect your liver or an antidepressant might affect your heart.
قد يؤثر على كبدك أو دواء مضاد للاكتئاب قد يؤثر على القلب.
These systems are really hard to build, but we're just starting to be able to get there,
هذه الأنظمة من الصعب بنائها حقاً، ولكن مؤخرا أصبح في إمكاننا الوصول إلى هناك،
and so, watch out.
ولذا، كونوا على اطلاع.
But that's not even all of it, because once a drug is approved,
ولكن هذا ليس حتى كل شيء، لأنه وبمجرد الموافقة على الدواء،
tissue engineering techniques can actually help us develop more personalized treatments.
فان تقنيات هندسة الأنسجة يمكنها فعلا مساعدتنا على تطوير علاجات فردية أكثر.
This is an example that you might care about someday,
وهذا مثال على ما قد يهمك يوما ما،
and I hope you never do,
وأرجو أن لا يحدث لك ابدأ،
because imagine if you ever get that call
لأن تخيل لو بلغك هذا الإتصال
that gives you that bad news that you might have cancer.
ينقل لك هذا الخبر السيئ بانه قد يكون لديك سرطان.
Wouldn't you rather test to see if those cancer drugs
ألن تحاول التجربة لمعرفة ما إذا كانت ادوية السرطان تلك
you're going to take are going to work on your cancer?
التي ستأخذها سوف تنجح في التفاعل مع سرطانك؟
This is an example from Karen Burg's lab, where they're
وهذا مثال من مختبر كارين بورغ، حيث أنهم
using inkjet technologies to print breast cancer cells
يستخدمون تقنيات الحبر النفاث لطباعة خلايا سرطان الثدي
and study its progressions and treatments.
ودراسة نموها وعلاجاتها.
And some of our colleagues at Tufts are mixing models
وبعض زملائنا في "تافتس" يقومون بخلط نماذج
like these with tissue-engineered bone to see how cancer
مثل هذه مع انسجة عظام مهندَسة لمعرفة كيف يقوم السرطان
might spread from one part of the body to the next,
بالانتشار من جزء لآخر في الجسم،
and you can imagine those kinds of multi-tissue chips
ويمكنك أن تتخيل تلك الأنواع من الرقائق النسيجية المتعددة
to be the next generation of these kinds of studies.
التي ستكون في الجيل القادم من هذه الأنواع من الدراسات.
And so thinking about the models that we've just discussed,
ولذاً، فبالنظر للنماذج التي ناقشناها للتو،
you can see, going forward, that tissue engineering
يمكنك أن ترى، أنه في المستقبل ستكون هندسة الأنسجة
is actually poised to help revolutionize drug screening
مستعدة فعلا للمساعدة على إحداث ثورة في اختبارات الادوية
at every single step of the path:
في كل خطوة في المسار:
disease models making for better drug formulations,
نماذج المرض التي ستجعل تركيبات الأدوية أفضل،
massively parallel human tissue models helping to revolutionize lab testing,
نماذج الأنسجة البشرية المتوازية ذات النطاق الواسع ستساعد على أحداث ثورة في تجارب المختبارات،
reduce animal testing and human testing in clinical trials,
الحد من التجارب الحيوانية والبشرية في اختبارات الأدوية،
and individualized therapies that disrupt
والعلاجات الفردية التي ستغير
what we even consider to be a market at all.
كل ما اعتبرناه سوقاً على الإطلاق.
Essentially, we're dramatically speeding up that feedback
حالياً، نحن نقوم بتسريع ردود الفعل تلك
between developing a molecule and learning about
التي تكون بين تطوير الجزيئة ومعرفة
how it acts in the human body.
كيف تتصرف في الجسم البشري.
Our process for doing this is essentially transforming
عملياتنا للقيام بذلك مبدئيا تنحول من
biotechnology and pharmacology into an information technology,
التكنولوجيا الحيوية والصيدلة إلى تكنولوجيا المعلومات،
helping us discover and evaluate drugs faster,
لمساعدتنا على اكتشاف وتقييم العقاقير أسرع،
more cheaply and more effectively.
وأرخص وأكثر فعالية.
It gives new meaning to models against animal testing, doesn't it?
أنها تعطينا معنىً جديداً لنماذج ضد التجارب على الحيوانات، أليس كذلك؟
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا. (تصفيق)